Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.22
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Awards, Gifts and Memorabilia, 1950-2007; XXII.
  - Attorney General of United States, 11.
    - Gift: Heavy brass bust of Lincoln on marble baseHonorable Dick Thornburgh, Attorney General of the United States; The Lincoln Club of Orange County, June 23, 1990
    - Plaque: The Dole Foundation for the Employment of Persons with Disabilities Recognizes United States Attorney General Richard L. Thornburgh "whose vision of equality under the law includes equal rights for all people with disabilities and whose wisdom and guidance have been crucial in paving the way for a more free and just society for people with disabilities with deep appreciation for outstanding leadership and commitment in the development and passage of the Americans With Disabilities Act", July 25, 1991
    - Plaque: To Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh from National Council of Juvenile and Family Court JudgesEvent: Dedication of Midby-Byron National Center for Judicial Education; Reno, Nevada, November 9, 1990 (Oversize 169)
    - Plaque: To Dick L. Thornburgh; Kent County Citizens with Disabilities, The Grand Rapids Center for Independent Living, Grand Rapids, Michigan; "In appreciation for his personal support and diligent efforts in helping to secure the passage of the Americans With Disabilities Act of 1990, October 18, 1990
    - Plaque: To Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh, Man of the Year in Government, "For dedicated Service and Outstanding Achievements" by Allegheny County League of Women Voters, April 17, 1990
    - Plaque: From Illinois States' Attorneys AssociationHonorable Dick Thornburgh Honorary Member, undated
    - Plaque: Dick Thornburgh "Statesman of Justice"; The Americans With Disabilities Act Award "43 Million Americans with Disabilities congratulate Attorney General Dick Thornburgh on his historic statesmanship for the enactment of The World's First Comprehensive Civil Rights Law for People with Disabilities Task Force on the Rights and Empowerments of Americans with Disabilities, October 12, 1990
    - Plaque: Richard Thornburgh, United States Attorney General, 19th Annual Law Day, Montgomery County Bar Association; Montgomery, Alabama, May 2, 1991
    - Plaque: Texas Police Association to Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh United States Attorney General "In honor of your generosity to and support of the Texas Police Association during its 90th Anniversary Conference and Seminar in Fort Worth, Texas", June 11-14, 1989
    - Plaque: National Sheriffs' Association Honorary Life Membership "…in the Advancement of Progressive Law Enforcement" [Handsome wooden plaque with incised lettering], June 26, 1990
    - Plaque: University of Louisville School of Law, Brandeis Lecture, To Dick Thornburgh, October 2, 1990 (Oversize 170)
    - Plaque: To Dick Thornburgh, United States Attorney General "…Contributions to municipal law enforcement"The California Police Chiefs Association 1991 Annual Conference, February 4, 1991
    - Plaque: To Dick Thornburgh, Attorney General of United States "In recognition of outstanding leadership"Hillsborough County Bar Association, November 8, 1990
    - Plaque: Ohio State University College of Law To Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh, Hooding Speaker, Spring 1990
    - Plaque: To Richard Thornburgh Attorney General of the United States, "…Dedication to the Enforcement of the Law and To a Safe Environment for All Persons and for your support of Memphis Area Neighborhood Watch, Inc."
    - Award: Engraved glass award, National Conference of Christians and Jews Defender of Justice Award "For Distinguished Civic Service" to Honorable Dick Thornburgh [HEAVY and quite handsome], August 20, 1990
    - Award: Cube on base; From Citizens Crime Committee of Delaware Valley to Dick Thornburgh United States Attorney General, Law Enforcement Appreciation Day, May 1, 1991
  - United Nations Under-Secretary General, 12.
    - Plaque: Small (c. 6: x 5) shield shaped wooden plaque: Class of '32 award to RLT '50; 10/17/92: Mercersburg Academy Emblem: "Service, achievement, character" (Oversize 161)
    - Plaque: Duquesne Univ. International Affairs Council, "recognition of distinguished public service", January 19, 1993
  - Ongoing Career, 13.
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Shippensburg University, May 7, 1994 (Oversize 6)
    - Certificate: Santa Rosa "Dick Thornburgh Day""Thornburgh becomes a cornerstone in the history of the fight for the total inclusion of all people in every segment of society…" [Framed certificate and plaque with Rotary International Seal], April 8, 1997 (Oversize 11)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Richard L. Thornburgh, Grove City College [Framed degree and hood], May 17, 2003 (Oversize 45)
    - Award: Santa Rosa, CA. Framed with gold seal from California Legislature, Independent Living Legacy Award from Community Resources for Independence to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh…"for their advocacy on behalf of people with disabilities in California and throughout the nation," [Handsome looking. Many Whereas'…re their accomplishments], May 7, 2004 (Oversize 46)
    - Award: Millersville University 150th Anniversary Medallion to The Honorable Richard Thornburgh "Recognizing extraordinary leadership and commitment to public higher education and societal issues." [Framed medallion on yellow ribbon with engraved brass plaque with the above wording. Decorative item] [For his role in signing the 1983 law that created the State System of Higher Education], September 10, 2004 (Oversize 51)
    - Plaque: The ARC Pennsylvania Award to Dick Thornburgh and Ginny Thornburgh [etching of family], June 1999 (Oversize 58)
    - Plaque: From Senator Heinz & The Urban League of Pittsburgh to Dick Thornburgh [art work], January 15, 1998 (Oversize 59)
    - Award: Chief Judge Damich, Court of Federal Claims to Dick Thornburgh, appointing honorary membership, November 4, 2005 (Oversize 65)
    - Award: Distinguished Alumni Fellow Award for Dick Thornburgh, University of Pittsburgh School of Law, February 24, 2006 (Oversize 68)
    - Plaque: Appreciation, from The Christian Council of Korea to Dick Thornburgh [pretty Oriental Frame], 2005 (Oversize 69)
    - Deed: Original Deed of Gift of Thornburgh Collection to University of Pittsburgh, [framed] Signed by: Dick Thornburgh, Mark A. Nordenberg, and Rush A. Miller, March 27, 1998 (Oversize 118)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Tiffin University [Framed], May 8, 1993 (Oversize 128)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Defiance College, May 7, 1995
    - Certificate: University of Pittsburgh, Omicron Delta Kappa Society "outstanding American who has exemplified the ideals of ODKA", March 23, 1996 (Oversize 129)
    - Certificate: State of Alabama, Governor's Office, naming Dick Thornburgh, Honorary Citizen of Alabama, April 11, 1997
    - Proclamation: City of Santa Rosa, CA, to Dick and Ginny Thornburgh, Independent Living Legacy Award for …"their tireless efforts…for persons with disabilities…", May 5, 2004
    - Honorary Degree: Clarion University of Pa, Doctor of Public Service, May 14, 1994 (Oversize 130)
    - Plaque: Ohio Attorney General's 1995 Conference on Law Enforcement, "gratitude for support and involvement in.....conference", October 5, 1995 (Oversize 160)
    - Plaque: Special Olympics – Dick Thornburgh Governor who initiated the games in 1981; XV anniversary [Big plaque with gold bell protruding], 1981-1996
    - Award: Round 6" heavy medal: XXIX World Affairs Council of Pittsburgh: David Glick Award to Dick Thornburgh, June 15, 1993 (Oversize 161)
    - Plaque: APSCUF, Richard Thornburgh "Recognition of distinguished contributions to cause of public higher education in PA" [handsome], April 21, 1995
    - Plaque: Massachusetts Coalition of Citizens with Disabilities: "Gratitude for unwavering commitment to ADA & civil and human rights of persons with disabilities", 1995
    - Plaque: From Rotary International, Santa Rosa & others: "In appreciation for advocacy to create a just and barrier free society for all people." [See OS 11], April 8, 1997
    - Plaque: Bronze hammered image of Cathedral of Learning, Commissioned by Chancellor of University of Pittsburgh (Oversize 162)
    - Award: Combination Lock Bank, October 1998
    - Gift: Clock given on occasion of awarding Honorary Degree to Dick Thornburgh by Clarion University of PA, May 14, 1994 (Oversize 164)
    - Gift: T-shirt: "TMI Alumni Association," from PA DER, [20 yr "anniversary"], January 11, 1999
    - Plaque: Richard L. Thornburgh: presented for exceptional contributions to World Peace and Mutual Understanding between Korea and U.S. Korean Alumni Association, University of Pittsburgh, 1995
    - Plaque: ASME INTERNATIONAL, The American Society of Mechanical Engineers "Certificate of Appreciation to Hon Dick Thornburgh, Roy V. Wright Lecturer, In recognition of his leadership in encouraging all engineers to discharge the duties, responsibilities and privileges of citizenship in our democracy" [Glass surface], 2002 (Oversize 166)
    - Plaque: In Esteem and Appreciation To Hon Richard Thornburgh "As keynote speaker at our 15th Annual Meeting you helped focus public attention on the work of NCCG. Your advocacy for Americans with disabilities, deepened by love and experience, is an inspiration to all of us." North Coast Community Homes, December 5, 2000
    - Plaque: To Dick Thornburgh "With sincere appreciation for your lifelong dedication to public service," NASP, Subrogation 2001: Improving the Odds, November 12, 2001
    - Award: Humanitarian Award presented to Richard L. Thornburgh, "Who has, in the true spirit of The Syria Shrine, embodied the virtue of public and humanitarian service, and who has worked tirelessly and selflessly for the people of Western Pennsylvania, the residents of this Commonwealth and the citizens of the United States of America," Syria Shrine, February 16, 2002
    - Award: VOLAR Champion Award (Volar Center for Independent Living) Americans with Disabilities ActGovernor. Dick Thornburgh; El Paso, Texas, July 23, 2004
    - Gift: Engraved round bronze plate (c. 8"). Back: To Richard L. Thornburgh, Franklin Area Chamber of Commerce, "In grateful appreciation for your address at our annual dinner." [Front: Building], April 4, 1995
    - Gift: Rotary Club of San Juan Puerto Rico; Round (3") metal medallion/paperweight
    - Plaque: With metal duplicate of Announcement card regarding Governor's return To Kirkpatrick & Lockhart to practice law [Metal pitted], February 1, 1987 (Oversize 167)
    - Plaque: University of Pittsburgh School of Law Commencement Speaker [Glass standing curved, etched "plaque" with University seal], May 23, 1998 (Oversize 171)
    - Plaque: Pittsburgh Council for International Visitors' International Bridge Award to The Honorable Dick Thornburgh "in recognition of his efforts to build bridges between Western Pennsylvania and the World," [Etched glass "plaque" with curved top, in wooden base], April 23, 2005
    - Plaque: "AARP Thanks Dick Thornburgh for Distinguished Leadership '16 Candles for the ADA' AARP Disability Interest Resource Group Launch, Washington D.C.", July 27, 2006
    - Plaque: Loyola University College of Law Commencement Speaker,[Plaque has photograph of Dick Thornburgh speaking], May 16, 2007
    - Gift: Round metal plate: Front: Picture of Harbison Chapel, Grove City College, Back: Hon. Dick Thornburgh, Installation Speaker, Inauguration of Richard G. Jewell '67, J.D., Eighth President of Grove City College,[brass c. 10" diameter, with stand], November 15, 2003
    - Award: Distinguished Alumni Fellow Award from University of Pittsburgh Round metal on ribbon with University seal on front Inscribed "Distinguished Alumni Fellow" Back: The Honorable Richard L. Thornburgh, Law '57, February 24, 2006
    - Award: Neighborhood Legal Services Association (HLSA) to Richard L. Thornburg [h missing]: "In recognition and appreciation for your deep commitment to the principle of Equal Justice Under Law NLSA 40th Anniversary, [Etched glass], April 28, 2006
    - Award: Saint Vincent College Presidential Medal of HonorDick Thornburgh [Large pewter looking medal on blue/white ribbon], May 7, 2003
  - Ginny Thornburgh, 14.
    - Plaque: Pittsburgh Jaycees, naming Virginia Thornburgh 1974 Human Relations Woman of the Year [picture of Point, and Ginny], January 26, 1975 (Oversize 24)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Public Service, Chatham College, "for her advocacy and work for rights and access for persons with disabilities." [Framed degree and hood], August 17, 2002 (Oversize 44)
    - Plaque: Appreciation from The Christian Council of Korea to Ginny Thornburgh [pretty Oriental Frame], 2005 (Oversize 70)
    - Certificate: To Mrs. Virginia Thornburgh, Community Services Award (CSP) "…leadership in health and welfare…", May 18, 1973 (Oversize 85)
    - Proclamation: To Ginny Thornburgh, from Forbes Hospice, "…exemplary care, compassion…", May 5, 1986 (Oversize 87)
    - Award: Tribute to Ginny Thornburgh by National Youth Aliyah Committee for Hadassah, "…promoted public awareness of needs of special children…", June 7, 1983 (Oversize 88)
    - Cartoon: Ginny Thornburgh "Kids Need Heroes" Cartoon, Child Guidance Center [leaving Governorship], 1987 (Oversize 121)
    - Photograph: Ginny Thornburgh in class interacting with children. (Oversize 122)
    - Certificate: Appreciation for "generosity and service in promoting objectives of..." National Secretaries Association, February 11, 1974 (Oversize 125)
    - Certificate: PA Committee on International Year of the Child, 1979
    - Certificate: National Exhibits by Blind Artists…Award for Exemplary Leadership in work with handicapped to Ginny Thornburgh, September 16, 1979
    - Resolution: Commendation by Commonwealth of PA State Board of Education, March 11, 1982
    - Citation: Montgomery County Community CollegePresidential Citation, June 4, 1982
    - Certificate: Appreciation by Shriners Hospitals for Crippled Children, "for the personal interest shown in the welfare of our little patients", April 19, 1983
    - Certificate: PA Hospice Network, In recognition and appreciation of "outstanding commitment to the hospice concept and unyielding encouragement to hospice staff and volunteers", October 3, 1985
    - Certificate: Easter Seal Society of Allegheny County50th Anniversary State Golden Lily Award, October 8, 1985
    - Certificate: Children's Hospital of PittsburghAppreciation of unique contribution, January 24, 1986
    - Certificate: Named a Paul Harris Fellow, Rotary Foundation of Rotary International, Undated
    - Proclamation: Gold Seal Proclamation by Governor Dick Thornburgh to Ginny Thornburgh honoring her birthday, January 7, 1980
    - Degree: Harvard University Master's Degree in EducationVirginia Judson [Framed], 1962
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Elizabethtown College, May 9, 1981 (Oversize 128)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Dickinson School of Law [with citation and program], May 31, 1986
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Mansfield State College, May 23, 1981 (Oversize 131)
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Wilson College, May 1, 1981
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Laws, Wheaton College, May 30, 1981
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Cabrini College, May 15, 1983
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Humane Letters, Cedar Crest College, May 22, 1983
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Public Service, Westminster College, April 17, 1994
    - Honorary Degree: Doctor of Public Service, Clarion University, May 13, 2000
    - Plaque: Juvenile Judges Commission Chairman's Award to Ginny Thornburgh, "for your support to the children of PA, October 13, 1983 (Oversize 142)
    - Plaque: PENNHURST CENTER June 30, 1986…[Piece of stone attached] "A little piece of Pennhurst to cherish forever" to Ginny Thornburgh, …recognition of contribution to Pennhurst's History of Service, Jan. 20, 1987 (Oversize 156)
    - Award: United Mental Health Agency Award "for distinction in field of mental retardation as an Advocate and educator on behalf of mentally Retarded citizens of Allegheny County", June 2, 1975 (Oversize 173)
    - Plaque: National Assn of Social Workers distinguished service award, June 4, 1980 (Oversize 174)
    - Plaque: Dorothea Lynde Dix Humanitarian Award, service to the handicapped, November 12, 1980
    - Plaque: PA Special Olympics award to Ginny and Dick Thornburgh [photo of them with Peter], 1982
    - Plaque: Barber Center Appreciation Award to Ginny and Dick Thornburgh for interest and concern for retarded citizens, 1952-1982
    - Plaque: Harcum Junior College Commencement Speaker, May 14, 1983
    - Plaque: AAOP Keystone Award for leadership role in improvement of services to chemically dependent citizens, 1983
    - Plaque: Distinguished Volunteer Leadership Award for leadership in the fight against birth defects, by March of Dimes
    - Plaque: JFK Memorial Award to Ginny Thornburgh in recognition of her significant contributions to Community Mental Health/Mental Retardation Movement in America; The Board of Directors of the Northeast Community Center for MH/MR, April 22, 1979 (Oversize 175)
    - Plaque: Association of Retarded Citizens award for generous support
    - Plaque: Recognition for meritorious service and personal commitment to clients and staff of Ebensburg Center
    - Plaque: Vision Thru Art Award in deep appreciation of her commitment to promoting art for the blind and sighted, April 28, 1985
    - Plaque: Bucks County Assn. for Retarded Citizens award for continuing efforts in expanding life opportunities for the developmentally disabled, June 28, 1980
    - Plaque: American Academy of Pediatrics award for support and help implementing initiatives of the "Speak up for Children" program, December 1979
    - Plaque: American Association on Mental Deficiency Region IX Leadership Award Presented to Ginny Thornburgh, October 22, 1982
    - Plaque: ORT social assistance award, February 21, 1973 (Oversize 176)
    - Plaque: Three Rivers Youth award for 6 years of dedicated service on Board of Directors
    - Plaque: Neighborhood Day Care Centers for your continuous support
    - Plaque: Westmoreland County Special Olympics award for outstanding efforts on their behalf, 1982
    - Plaque: PA Psychological Assoc public service award for outstanding contributions to human welfare, June 19, 1979
    - Plaque: In appreciation for participation in WHP Station birthday, Hershey Park, PA, May 28, 1979
    - Plaque: YMCA Camp, for participation in annual meeting, and recognitions of intention to underwrite in her name sending underprivileged youngsters to the camp, May 16, 1979
    - Plaque: Certificate of appreciation to Ginny Thornburgh for outstanding service to Volunteers of American, April 5, 1980
    - Plaque: Lee Hospital Award, October 19, 1984 (Oversize 177)
    - Plaque: Disabled American Veterans award for outstanding dedication to the needs of disabled and handicapped persons, June 19, 1984
    - Plaque: County Treasurer's Association for outstanding message as speaker, June 17, 1983
    - Plaque: Veterans award to outstanding and dedicated service to children and youth programs, March 1983
    - Plaque: United Negro College fund award in recognition of dedicated service in meeting needs of special children and in unselfish time and talent given for betterment of the community, January 29, 1982
    - Plaque: National Society for Autistic children award for uncommon sensitivity, courage, and dignity in providing example and encouragement for advocates for developmentally disabled people, 1981
    - Plaque: ACLU award honoring outstanding dedication to rights of mentally retarded, December 12, 1979
    - Plaque: Committee to Combat Huntington's Disease award for one who inspires through devotion, May 15, 1981 (Oversize 178)
    - Plaque: Alpha Kappa Alpha Sorority award to first lady at health happening fair, 1981
    - Plaque: Veterans Administration for outstanding service and recognition of needs of the handicapped, May 15, 1981
    - Plaque: PA Council of Administrators of Special Education recognition for 8 years of commitment and dedication to exception children as PA's first lady, November 3, 1986
    - Plaque: Shippensburg University in recognition of distinguished achievement and personal service for the benefit of the citizens of the commonwealth, May 19, 1986
    - Plaque: Governor's Committee on Employment for the Handicapped [Metal plate with wording loose from the wooden backing], November 6, 1985
    - Plaque: Presented to Ginny Thornburgh by the, Vocational Rehabilitation Center in recognition of long and dedicated record, and as an advocate for the rights of Disabled people, January 26, 1983 (Oversize 179)
    - Plaque: Juvenile Law Award, in recognition and appreciation of the significant contributions rendered by Virginia Judson Thornburgh to the field of juvenile justice and child welfare in the commonwealth of Pennsylvania, Juvenile Law Committee, the Allegheny County Bar Association, Pittsburgh, PA, Richard S. Levine, Chairperson, 1986
    - Plaque: Resolution from PA Federation of Women's Clubs to Ginny Thornburgh, and electing her to honorary membership, May 19, 1984
    - Plaque: Presented to Ginny Thornburgh by Women's American ORT, Philadelphia Region [clear plaque], 1985
    - Plaque: Small round plaque on base: Thanks to Ginny Thornburgh, LARC, Inc. [Partners in Rehabilitation]
    - Award: To Ginny Thornburgh Outstanding volunteer[small item on clear base with etched dove]
    - Award: Small heavy steel beam: Ginny Thornburgh Member of BIG SHOP PRIDE TEAM, Homestead Works, [similar given to Governor], 1980
    - Award: J.C. Penny Golden Rule Award to Ginny Thornburgh [marble base with "brass" vertical emblem]
    - Award: Virginia Thornburgh, Rotary Foundation of Rotary International, Named a Paul Harris Fellow "in appreciation of tangible and significant assistance given for the furtherance of better understanding and friendly relations between peoples of the world, undated (Oversize 180)
    - Award: Paul Harris Medal in blue velvet box with colored ribbon
    - Award: Inglis House Disability Awareness Award, Presented to Ginny Thornburgh "in recognition of her outstanding accomplishments which promote greater public understanding and awareness of the needs and abilities of persons with physical disabilities"INGLIS HOUSE, a WHEELCHAIR COMMUNITY, October 16, 1996
    - Award: Seal of U.S. President's Committee on Mental Retardation Award Metal plate: Virginia J. Thornburgh, Committee Member, 1982-1987
    - Plaque: Pennsylvania Special Olympics, To "Special Friend Virginia Thornburgh," "Too often the mentally challenged are told 'you can't do it.' Special Olympics says 'you can do it.' All you need is a chance. Thank you for giving that chance to the Special Olympians of Pennsylvania."
    - Plaque: The Martin Luther Home Society Board of Directors Honors "Ginny Thornburgh Person of the Year for 1996, In recognition of dedicated leadership and caring as a parent, writer, speaker, and advocate for persons with disabilities" Seal at the bottom: "LOVE, HOPE, CARING, LEADERSHIP"
    - Plaque: Inscribed metal plate, "It's all about community! Learning from people with mental retardation" Award presented to Ginny Thornburgh by National Organization on Disabilities, "For inspiring us to move From Barriers to Bridges That All May Worship" Philadelphia Office of Mental Health and Mental Retardation, October 22, 1996